Guide to the Al cantío de un gallo Radio Program Audio Recordings
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Al cantío de un gallo radio program audio recordings
1988-1999
MS 1960
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
7.75
(602 audiocassettes and 1box)
The collection consists of audio recordings of Al cantío de un gallo radio program, as well as a small number of recordings of other radio programs. Al cantío de un gallo broadcast news (political, economic, cultural, and social), commentaries, interviews, and some music, pertaining to Cuba and Cuban exiles. The primary contributors were Carlos Franqui and Alfredo Melero. The recordings offer insight into the Cuban revolution, conditions in Cuba under Castro, resistance to Castro rule, and the Cuban exile experience. The program ran from the late 1980s through the 1990s.
Franqui, Carlos, 1921-2010
Melero, Alfredo
Biographical / Historical
Al cantío de un gallo was a radio program broadcast by Cuban exiles Carlos Franqui and Alfredo Melero into Cuba, largely from Puerto Rico, Florida, and Central America, via a clandestine radio station called La Voz del CID. La Voz posited itself as the "voice of the opposition" (to Fidel Castro). The radio program, generally critical of Fidel Castro and his government consisted of news (political, economic, cultural, and social), commentaries, interviews, and some music. The program was produced by the Huber Matos' Cuba Independiente y Democrática (CID). Carlos Franqui and Huber Matos were both part of the revolutionary movement that helped Castro overthrow the Batista regime. They became disenchanted with Castro, objecting to his authoritarianism and shift to communism. In 1959, Matos was charged with treason and jailed by Castro, eventually released in 1979. He went into exile in the United States, where he founded CID and became one of the most important participants in the opposition to the Castro regime. Carlos Franqui (1921-2010) was a journalist, writer, poet, and prominent member of the revolutionary movement. He ran Radio Rebelde, was the editor of Revolucíon, and, later, was a major contributor to Lunes de revolución. After becoming critical of Castro and the revolutionary government, Franqui was exiled from Cuba in the 1960s and lived first in Europe and then Puerto Rico, where he died in 2010. His many publications include the periodical Carta de Cuba (with Alfredo Melero); Diario de la Revolución cubana; Cuba, la revolución, ¿mito o realidad?; Retrato de familias con Fidel; and Vida, aventuras y desastres de un hombre llamado Castro. In addition to his work on Al cantío de un gallo, Alfredo Melero was co-founder of Carta de Cuba and a coordinator of Cuba Independiente y Democrática (CID). Al cantío de un gallo ran from the late 1980s through the 1990s.
Arrangement
The tapes are arranged by tape number assigned by the repository.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of approximately 1000 audio recordings of the Al cantío de un gallo radio program, as well as a small number of recordings of other radio programs. Al cantío de un gallo broadcast news (political, economic, cultural, and social), commentaries, interviews, and some music, pertaining to Cuba and Cuban exiles. The primary contributors were Carlos Franqui and Alfredo Melero, but frequent guest contributors included: Rodolfo Silva, Felipe Rodriguez, and Amalia Montijo. Interviewees included independent reporters, exiles and emigrants, former prisoners, activists, Cubans living in Cuba, leaders of exile organizations, and writers. The program provided news and information the producers believed was suppressed by the Cuban government and provided a venue for independent news reporting. Common topics include Fidel Castro; Carlos Franqui; human rights violations; living conditions; the revolution of 1959 and earlier revolutions; Jose Martí; the exile experience; significant events, such as the sinking of the tugboat "13 de Marzo"; relations with other countries, especially Russia, United States and China; and writers and literature. Al cantío de un gallo ran through Cuba's "special period" (1990-1996), a period of economic crisis brought on by the collapse of the Soviet Union. As such, the economy is another major theme in the program throughout the 1990s. Economic topics include the United States embargo, foreign investment, tourism, and prostitution. Melero and Franqui also describe Cuba before 1959, with an emphasis on the loss of freedom, culture, and traditions. The recordings offer insight into the Cuban revolution, conditions in Cuba under Castro, resistance to Castro's rule, and the Cuban exile experience. The recordings are on sixty- and ninety-minute audiocassettes with one program per side. Each radio program has approximately twenty minutes of content. The original cassette insert labels were retained and filed at the end of the collection.
Custodial History
Purchased by and transferred from the Latin American Curator, 2009.
General
This collection was digitized through the generous support of the Arcadia Foundation.
Existence and Location of Copies
The entire collection is available in digital form.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
The entire collection is digitized. Researchers must use the digital use copies instead of the originals.
Original audiovisual materials, as well as preservation and duplicating masters, may not be played. Researchers wishing to obtain an additional copy for their personal use should consult Copying Services information on the Manuscripts and Archives web site.
Exiles, Cuban -- History -- 20th Century; Cuba -- History -- 1959-1990; Cuba -- History -- Revolution, 1959; Cuba -- Politics and government -- 1959-; Radio programs; Castro, Fidel, 1926-2016; Franqui, Carlos, 1921-2010
- Tape 1, 1988 July 26; 1 (Box 1)
  Summary (English)
  Side A: A speech made on July 26th, 1988. The recording has a lot of transmission noise.
  Side B: Second part of the July 26th, 1988, speech, also with a lot of transmission noise.
  Summary (Spanish)
  Side A: Un discurso de 26 del julio de 1988 con mucho ruido de transmisión.
  Side B: Segunda parte del discurso del 26 de julio de 1988, aun con mucho ruido de transmisión.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 2, 1988 December; 1 (Box 2)
  Side A: Interview with Carlos Franqui. Franqui discusses the letter that Cuban exiles have sent Castro challenging him to a referendum to see if, 30 years after the beginning of his government, Cuba wants him to hold free elections. He goes on to compare Castro and Chile's dictator Augusto Pinochet, who called for free elections after a similar referendum. Franqui answers Melero's questions regarding peaceful protest, the political role of youth and Cuba's liberation history. Franqui refers to his book, Life, adventures and disasters of a man named Fidel Castro.
  Side B: Music Program. Vikki Carr: "Grande, grande, grande". Roberto Carlos: "Que será de ti". Katunga: "Muchacha traviesa, dame tu amor". Pedro Tamayo: "Aquí no, que va". Rocío Durcal: "No sirvo para estar sin ti". Yergo: "Entre una espada y la pared". Mocedades: "Eres Tu". Camilo Sesto: "Quién lo diría". Jaime Marques: "África, Brasil te ama". José Feliciano: "Camino verde". [Unknown song].
  Side A: Entrevista con Carlos Franqui. Franqui habla sobre una carta escrita por exiliados cubanos que le exige a Castro un plebiscito para celebrar los 30 años de su gobierno. El plebiscito, como el que tomó efecto en Chile y dio fin a la dictadura de Augusto Pinochet, daría legitimidad popular a la continuación de su gobierno o lo haría llamar a elecciones libres. Franqui compara las dictaduras de Castro y Pinochet. Franqui contesta las preguntas de Melero sobre protestas pacíficas, el partido juvenil y la historia de la independencia cubana. Franqui termina por referirse a su libro, Vida, aventuras, y desastres de un hombre llamado Fidel Castro.
  Side B: Programa musical. Se pone Vikki Carr: "Grande, grande, grande". Roberto Carlos: "Qué será de tí". Katunga: "Muchacha traviesa, dame tu amor". Pedro Tamayo: "Aquí no, que va". Rocío Durcal: "No sirvo para estar sin ti". Yergo: "Entre una espada y la pared". Mocedades: "Eres Tu". Camilo Sesto: "Quien lo diría". Jaime Marques: "África, Brasil te ama". Jose Feliciano: "Camino verde". [Canción desconocida.]
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 3, 1989 February 26; 1 (Box 3)
  Side A: Panel discussion: the applicability of Jose Marti's thought in contemporary times. Chubaya, Carmen; Marrero, Levi; Cuadra, Ángel; Figueroa, Javier; Candelaria, Andrés; Melero, Alfredo. Chubayan follows with an invocation and introduces the panel. Candelaria is moderating and Melero, coordinator of CID (Cuba Independiente Democrática), is present. The panel discusses what aspects of Cuban national hero and intellectual Jose Martí can be appropriated for Cuba's current political situation. A brief summary of Martí's life and his historical context is given.
  Side B: Continuation of the Panel discussion on the applicability of Jose Martí's thought in contemporary times. Chubaya Carmen. Marrero, Levi; Cuadra, Ángel; Figueroa, Javier; Candelaria, Andrés; Melero, Alfredo. The speaker emphasizes Martí's help in the Cuban war of independence through the unification of the émigré community in Florida, which echoes Cuban society's division between the diaspora and those still on the island. They then talk about his thoughts on the Cuban war of independence, the American continent and Simon Bolívar.
  Side A: Chubayan recita una invocación e introduce el panel de locutores. Candelaria es el moderador y Melero, el coordinador del CID, está presente. Los locutores discuten cuáles aspectos del pensamiento de José Martí, el héroe cubano, aún están vigentes. Hay un pequeño resumen de la vida de Martí y el contexto histórico en el que se desenvolvió.
  Side B: Los locutores destacan la influencia de Martí en la unificación de la comunidad cubana en Florida y su influencia en la guerra de independencia. Lo ven como un reflejo de la situación actual y la división entre los exiliados y aquellos cubanos aún en la isla. Se habla de la relación de Martí con la independencia cubana y su percepción de América y Simón Bolívar.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 4, 1991 June; 1 (Box 4)
  Side A: Speech about the situation of Cuba: the hardships of life on the island and the humiliation of being exiled. The speaker is hopeful about the end of Castro's regime, particularly following the very quick end of the USSR, which transpired with very few deaths.
  Side B: Convención Anual de 1991 de Cuba Independiente y Democrática. Peña Martínez, Oscar; Abí Cobas, Hirán; Moya Alfonso, David. Hirán Abí Cobas from the Cuban Human Rights Party and David Moya Alfonso, member of the World Federation of Democratic Youth and the Cuban Human Rights Party.
  Side A: Discurso sobre la situación actual de Cuba: las dificultades de la vida en la isla y la humillación del exilio. La caída de la Unión Soviética en poco más de una semana, y las pocas muertes que ese cambio político generó, dan al narrador esperanza de que el fin del gobierno de Castro se aproxime.
  Side B: Convención Anual de 1991 de Cuba Independiente y Democrática. Peña Martínez, Oscar; Abí Cobas, Hirán; Moya Alfonso, David. Hirán Abí Cobas de Partido Pro Derechos Humanos de Cuba y David Moya Alfonso, miembro de la Federación Mundial de Juventud Democrática y el Partido Pro Derechos Humanos.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 5, 1991 June; 1 (Box 5)
  Side A: Marrero talks about the history of Cuba and how Cuba has no history of democratic self-government due to the political system applied by Spain during colonial times. He says that Cuba had a history of quality education before the dictatorship and that current indoctrination is failing.
  Side B: Tape begins twice. Marrero describes Cuba's impressive environmental resources. He says that despite this Castro is turning Cuba back into what it was in the times of Spanish colonialism, as seen in the terrible living conditions on the island. He then gives the historical background of the genetic make-up of the Cuban population.
  Side A: Marrero explica que, debido al sistema político implementado por España en la Cuba colonial, el pueblo cubano no tiene un legado democrático ni experiencia en el autogobierno. Por el otro lado, la educación en Cuba siempre ha sido de muy buena calidad en comparación con los demás países latinoamericanos. Marrero también comenta su percepción de que el adoctrinamiento en Cuba está fallando.
  Side B: La cinta comienza dos veces. Marrero describe los recursos naturales de Cuba. Dice que Castro está convirtiendo a Cuba en lo que fue en la época colonial, como se ve en las pésimas condiciones de vida en la isla. Procede a resumir la historia genética del pueblo cubano.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 6, 1991 June; 1 (Box 6)
  Side A: Guedez, Emilio; Cesteves, Emil; Martínez, Manuel; Sanz, Paquita; Álvarez, Mario; Melero, Alfredo. Guedez discusses the ideals behind the Cuban revolution, the political situation in the months following the revolution, and the difference between the democratic "26 de Julio" and the communist orientation of Castro. Castro has tried to legitimize his usurpation of power by aligning with the communist political forces.
  Side B: Many little segments by Máximo Gómez Radio: A comparison of different forms of government (dictatorship versus democracy); followed by a segment called, "Se llama José Martí," that includes anti-Marxist quotes by Martí; finally a segment called, "Trinchera de Ideas," where the distinction between authentic and counterrevolutionary -or exiled- Cubans is questioned.
  Side A: Guedez, Emilio; Cesteves, Emil; Martínez, Manuel; Sanz, Paquita; Álvarez, Mario; Melero, Alfredo. Guedez habla sobre los ideales que inspiraron la revolución cubana y la situación política de la isla en los primeros meses después de la revolución, delineando la diferencia entre el 26 de Julio, una organización democrática, y la influencia comunista sobre Castro. Opina que Castro ha intentado legitimar su poder alineándose con fuerzas comunistas.
  Side B: La grabación incluye varios segmentos pequeños, entre ellos: una comparación de distintas formas de gobierno (dictadura versus democracia), un segmento llamado "Se llama José Martí" con citas anti-Marxistas del intelectual y "Trinchera de Ideas", donde se desmiente la distinción entre cubanos auténticos y exiliados.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 7, 1992 September 25; 1 (Box 7)
  General
  The recording is inaudible.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 8, 1992 November 20; 1 (Box 8)
  Side A: Press conference with former first dancer of the National Ballet of Cuba, Jorge Esquivel, who has received political asylum in Puerto Rico. Esquivel says that the worse the embargo gets, the faster Castro's dictatorship will end. Any economic support will only delay the future uprising. He also talks about the expressions of dissent on the island by youth, musicians, and through involvement with organizations like CID, etc.
  Side B: Continuation of the press conference with Jorge Esquivel. He foresees a civil war due to the poor living conditions in Cuba and the instability of the government after the media problems with drug trafficking and the case of Arnaldo Ochoa.
  Side A: Conferencia de prensa con el primer bailarín del Ballet Nacional de Cuba, Jorge Esquivel, quien ha recibido asilo político en Puerto Rico. Esquivel opina que cuanto peor sea el embargo de Cuba, mas rápido caerá el gobierno de Castro. Cualquier apoyo económico simplemente ayudar a perpetuar su gobierno. También habla sobre las formas de expresión de disidencia política en la isla por parte de la juventud, los músicos y a través de organizaciones como CID, etc.
  Side B: Continuación de la conferencia de prensa con el bailarín Jorge Esquivel. Dice que prevé una guerra civil debida a las malas condiciones de vida en Cuba y la falta de estabilidad política luego de las noticias relacionando al gobierno con el narcotráfico y el caso de Arnaldo Ochoa.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 9, 1993 January; 1 (Box 9)
  Side A: Melero and Franqui compare Haiti and Cuba. Franqui notes that this is not a racial issue, but a national problem, and compares Cuba's economic, political and moral destruction with Haiti's past. Franqui then makes the distinction between Castro and Cuba and reminds listeners that it is legitimate to love Cuba and yet hate Castro.
  Side B: The speaker comments on Castro's September 5, 1992, speech decreeing the end of the construction of Juraguá Nuclear Power Plant due to the fall of the USSR and lack of funds. According to Franqui, the reactors meant 1,200 million dollars from Cuba and the preparation of more than 10 thousand Cuban workers and engineers specialized for work in nuclear plants that are now jobless. They then discuss the USSR's relationship to Cuba.
  Side A: Melero y Franqui hablan sobre la posible haitianización de Cuba. Franqui comenta que no es un asunto racial, sino una mala situación nacional en general -comparando la destrucción política, económica y moral de Cuba con el pasado de Haití. Franqui luego recuerda a los oyentes que hay una diferencia entre Castro y Cuba, por lo que se puede amar al país al mismo tiempo que se odia al líder.
  Side B: Los locutores discuten la construcción de la Central Electronuclear (CEN) de Juraguá, dio término a la que Castro el 5 de Septiembre de 1992, debido al término de la Unión Soviética y la falta de recursos nacionales. Según Franqui, la central significó 1,200 millones de dólares americanos invertidos por Cuba y la especialización de 10 mil trabajadores cubanos, quienes ahora no tienen dónde trabajar.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 10, 1993 January; 1 (Box 10)
  Side A: Melero and Franqui discuss a January 4th, New York Times article by Ginger Thompson titled, "Castro relaxes grip on Cuba's churches, move seen as bid to bolster support." They point out that people's displeasure with the government has become more vocal which signals the approach of the end of Castro's government. They then discuss Major Orestes Lorenzo's December 19, 1992, successful attempt to rescue his family. San Lorenzo.
  Side B: Melero reads Franqui's article "La obra trascendental de Levi Marrero", on the geographer and historian Levi Marrero's epic work, Cuba: economía y sociedad. Franqui's article summarizes Marrero's work and explains its historical importance and relevance for Cuba.
  Side A: Melero y Franqui hablan sobre un artículo del 4 de enero de 1993 en el New York Times titulado, "Castro relaja su control sobre la iglesia; cambio percibido como una forma de incrementar popularidad," por Ginger Thompson. Notan que la falta de apoyo al gobierno se está volviendo más pública, lo que los hace pensar que predice el fin del gobierno de Castro se está acercando. Luego comentan el rescate de la familia del Mayor Orestes Lorenzo en diciembre de 1992.
  Side B: Melero lee el artículo de Franqui "La obra trascendental de Levi Marrero", sobre la obra importante del geógrafo e historiador, Levi Marrero, Cuba: economía y sociedad. El artículo de Franqui resume el trabajo de Marrero y explica tanto su importancia histórica como su relevancia para el pueblo cubano.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 11, 1993 January; 1 (Box 11)
  Side A: The speakers talk about the deterioration of Cuba, and the "individual solutions" that are arising to the problems of life on the island: suicide and desertion when possible. Silva encourages listeners to stop thinking in terms of individual solutions, and all three speakers believe it's time to overthrow Castro's government. They argue that Orestes Lorenzo's success proves that national security is not functioning as well as it did in the past and that the Cuban people should take advantage of that.
  Side B: Franqui argues that there is nothing to lose by coming together to remove Castro from power and also explains how to go about it. Franqui then explains that they will have help and resources from the Cuban exiles to help with the subsequent reconstruction of the island. Silva then clarifies that the diaspora does not encourage a revolution for its own good but for the good of those Cubans on the island that no longer have the means to survive. The speakers agree that though they do not suffer from material needs like those on the island, they do want to see their homeland free from a dictatorship out of a sense of nationalism.
  Side A: Los locutores hablan sobre el deterioro de Cuba y sobre las soluciones individuales que el pueblo cubano está ocupando contra los problemas en la isla: la deserción dentro de lo posible o el suicidio. Silva le pide a los oyentes que no sigan buscando soluciones individuales y los tres locutores opinan que es hora de deshacerse de Castro por vías colectivas (revolución). Argumentan que el éxito de Orestes Lorenzo prueba que la seguridad nacional no funciona como antes y que el pueblo cubano debería apróvecharse de eso.
  Side B: Franqui argumenta que el pueblo de Cuba no tiene nada que perder haciendo una revolución y describe cómo alguien puede organizarse pasando sin estar percibido. Luego explica que si se revelán el pueblo cubano, tendrá la ayuda y el apoyo económico de los Cubanos exiliados al momento de reconstruír el país. Silva clarifica que los exiliados no quieren una revolución por su propio bien, sino por el bien de aquellos en la isla que no tienen cómo subsistir. Los locutores están de acuerdo con que a pesar de que no estén sufriendo por faltas materiales, sufren por la situación de Cuba debido a un sentido de patriotismo.
  - Preservation masters, 2
  - Use copies, 2
- Tape 12, 1993 June 18; 1 (Box 12)
  Side A: The speakers discuss the coming reduction of the Cuban army: the reasons, the methods and the consequences. The reason, they believe, is the end of the USSR and Cuba's inability to afford such a disproportionally large army (the biggest per capita in America, according to the speakers' opinion). The reduction will probably be used as a cover for the selective expulsion of democratic forces within the army.
  Side B: Second part of the panel discussion on the reduction of the Cuban army. The speakers argue that things in Cuba will not be resolved with a simple influx of resources, but rather the Cuban people have to begin producing at levels previously only possible through a capitalist economic model. They explain that financing for private endeavors will exist, not as a gift from the government but as a loan from another private enterprise that will take into consideration the person's ability to pay back the loan later. Because of this, the speakers think that though capitalism demands more work, it allows people to improve their condition through their effort without depending on something else, like the government.
  Side A: Los locutores comentan la noticia de que las fuerzas armadas de Cuba serán reducidas e intentan determinar las razones detrás de la medida, los métodos que se utilizarán y las consecuencias de tal medida. Piensan que la motivación detrás de la medida es el reciente colapso de la Unión Soviética y la falta de recursos en Cuba para mantener el ejército per cápita más grande de América. Los locutores opinan que la reducción será usada como excusa para la depuración de fuerzas democráticas dentro de las fuerzas armadas.